Guide to the Ira Gruber academic papers, 1934-2022 UA 204
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Ira Gruber academic papers
1934-2022
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Gruber, Ira D., Dr.
UA 204
22.75 Linear Feet 24 boxes
Collection contains the academic writings, professional and personal correspondence, courses taught, and biographical information of Ira Gruber before and while a professor of History at Rice University.
Biographical Note
Ira Gruber was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania January 6, 1934. Pottstown, Pennsylvania was the town of residence. In 1951 Ira Gruber began studies at Duke University. While at Duke University Ira Gruber was a part of the United States Naval Reserve. July of 1955 Ira Gruber was called to active duty. He served on the USS Wiltsie were he was appointed a crypto security officer. Ira Gruber was released of active duty June 1957. Ira Gruber completed his undergraduate studies at Duke University (1955), and also received his PhD from Duke in 1961.
In 1961-62 Dr. Gruber was an instructor of history at Duke University. 1962-65 Dr. Gruber was a fellow at the Institute of Early American History and Culture. 1965-66 Dr. Gruber was an assistant professor of History at Occidental College. 1966 to 2008 Ira Gruber was professor of history at Rice University (Houston). During the time at Rice, Dr. Gruber was Masterson Department of History Chair from 1983-87. Rice University being a residential college system, Dr. Gruber served as Hanszen College Master from 1968-73. In 1979 Dr. Gruber held the position of John F. Morrison Professor at the U.S. Army Command and General Staff College. This position was as a visiting professor and ended in 1980. Dr. Gruber took another visiting professor position with the U.S. Military Academy in 1984-85. Ira Gruber retired from Rice University in 2008.
Ira Gruber received the George R. Brown Award for Excellence in Teaching at Rice in 2001, as well as the George R. Brown Award for Superior Teaching twice, once in 1974 and again in 2003. While publishing many articles, this major writings have been on Early American History and Warfare. His major books are: The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, Warfare in Western World: Military Operations Since 1871, and John Peebles' American War: The Diary of a Scottish Grenadier
Scope and Contents Note
The Ira Gruber Papers from 1934 – 2022 include correspondence of faculty meetings, recommendations on faculty and graduate students, personal letters, course development, and professional writings. Papers on the development and revisions of his four major writings, The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, Warfare in Western World: Military Operations Since 1871, John Peebles' American War: The Diary of a Scottish Grenadier and Books and the British Army at the Time of the American Revolution. Also contained in this collection are Ira Gruber's papers on the courses he developed and taught including notes and exams. The papers and correspondence on his service for development of course distribution credit, faculty handbook, and professional vitae. Personal appointment calendars and papers dealing with his involvement in the Champions Golf Club are also contained within collection.
Conditions Governing Access Note
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
This collection was donated by Dr. Ira Gruber in 2006, 2010, 2012, 2013, 2016, 2019, 2020, 2021 and 2022.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Rice University -- History; Education; War; Soldiers -- Correspondence; College teachers
Document Types
memorabilia; memorandums; letters (correspondence); typescripts; lecture notes; personal correspondence; Correspondence; photographs; notes; syllabi; manuscripts (document genre); publications
Places
Houston (Tex.) -- History.
- Series I: Books, 1967-1998; 79704; 6 Linear Feet
  - Reference Materials for The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 79791 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Maps for The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 1971, 79790 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence RE: Howe Brothers and North Ministry, 1967-1971, 79789 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Search for Howe MSS in U.S., 1962-1963, 79788 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Spelling, Capitalization, Usage, 79787 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Guides and Notes for preparing typescript, 1961, 1968, 79786 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - M.S. Version I: The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 79785 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Howe Brothers scaffolding IV-VII, 79784 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Howe Brothers scaffolding VIII-IX, 79783 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Howe Brothers scaffolding X-XII, 1969, 79782 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Essays on Selected Sources, 79781 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M.S. Version II: The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 79780 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Howe Brothers Precis of M.S. chapter by chapter, 79779 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. II, 79778 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. III, 79777 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. IV, 79776 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. V, 79775 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. VI, 79774 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. VII, 79773 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. VIII, 79772 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. IX, 79771 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. X, 79770 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. XI, 79769 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Howe Brothers M.S. XII, 79768 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Index: The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 79767 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Index II: The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 1972, 79766 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Reviews of The Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, Royalities Reports, 1972-2000, 79765 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Reference Materials for Warfare in the Western World, 1991-1994, 79764 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Heath Text, Early Correspondence, 1985, 79763 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Heath, History of Art of War: current critical discussion of the argument, 1990-1995, 79762 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence RE: Proofreading Warfare in Western World, 1994-1997, 79761 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Standardized Spellings: Heath Text, 79760 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - M.S. I "Scaffolding" - Warfare in the Western World, 79759 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Scaffolding ch. 1: Gustavus Adolphus and the Military Revolution, 79758 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scaffolding ch. II, 79757 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Outline ch. III, 79756 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scaffolding III: Limited War in Europe 1714-1763, 79755 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scaffolding ch. IV: USMA (United States Military Academy) Text, 79754 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scaffolding ch. V USMA, 79753 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scaffolding, September 1994, 79752 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Drafts of maps for USMA: text ch. I-V, 1994, 79751 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Suggestions for revisions: IG's draft USMA text, 1991-1992, 79750 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1st version 1989: Gustavus Adolphus and the Military Revolution, 79749 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Working Draft ch. II, 79748 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Residue Composition USMA: ch. III, 79747 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Typescript ch. III, 79746 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Draft ch. IV: USMA text, 79745 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Working Typescript ch. IV: USMA, 79744 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Working Typescript ch. V, 79743 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - M.S. Draft ch. V: USMA, 79742 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - M.S. ch. I-IV, Warfare in the Western World: Used in course Hist. 382, 1993, 79741 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Typescript: Warfare in the Western World, 79740 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Final Typescript: Warfare in the Western World, 1994, 79739 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Illustrations: Health ch. I-V, 1994, 79738 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Research/Correspondence on John Peebles, 79737 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - John Peebles: Correspondence with Army Records Society, 1993-1998, 79736 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - John Peebles Journal ch. 1-2, 79735 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - John Peebles Journal ch. 3-4, 79734 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - John Peebles Journal ch. 5-6, 79733 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - John Peebles Journal ch. 7-10, 79732 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - John Peebles Journal ch. 11-12, 79731 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - John Peebles Journal ch. 13-14, 79730 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Draft 1: John Peebles, 79729 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Additions, corrections for Peebles; Am W Sept. 1996 - Feb. 1997, 79728 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Draft 2: John Peebles, 79727 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - John Peebles corrected ch. 1-3, 79726 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Draft 2: John Peebles (con't), 79725 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Peebles Corrected Typescript 7-10, 79724 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Peebles Corrected ch. 11-14, 79723 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Peebles Footnotes, 79722 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Appendix "A:" Biographical Sketches, 79721 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Peebles Appendix "B", 79720 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Catalogue of Omissions: Appendix "C" Peebles Notebook, 79719 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Peebles Additions and Corrections, February 1997, 79718 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Peebles Maps, 79717 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Typescript, John Peebles, 79716 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - John Peebles: Appendix and Index, 79715 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - John Peebles Edited Proof; 1 of 3, 1997, 79714 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - John Peebles Edited Proof, 2 of 3, 1997, 79713 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - John Peebles Edited Proof, 3 of 3, 1997, 79712 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - John Peebles 1st Page Proof, 1 of 3, 1997, 79711 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - John Peebles 1st Page Proof, 2 of 3, 1997, 79710 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - John Peebles 1st Page Proof, 3 of 3, 1997, 79709 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - John Peebles 3rd Page Proof, 1 of 3, 1997, 79708 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - John Peebles 3rd Page Proof, 2 of 3, 1997, 79707 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - John Peebles 3rd Page Proof, 3 of 3, 1997, 79706 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Oversize: Galley of the Howe Brothers and the American Revolution, 1972, 79705 (Box 15, Folder -)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1953-2008; 79621; 7 Linear Feet; (7 boxes)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1953-1958, 79703 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Naval Service Records, 1955-1957, 79702 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Resignation from Naval Reserves 1-55-1968, 79701 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - I. Gruber, USS Wiltsie, 1955-1956, 2008, 79700 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Personal and General Correspondence, 1959-1961, 79699 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1962, 79698 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan - May 1963, 79697 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, June - Dec. 1963, 79696 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan - Dec 1964, 79695 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1965, 79694 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1965, 79693 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1967, 79692 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1968, 79691 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1969, 79690 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970, 79689 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1971, 79688 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1972, 79687 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1973, 79686 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1974 1 of 2, 79685 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1974 2 of 2, 79684 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1975, 79683 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1976, 79682 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1977, 79681 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1978, 79680 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979, 79679 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980, 79678 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence RE: 5700 Pine Street, 1979-1980, 79677 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980, 79676 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1981, 79675 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Accounting for Research in Britian, 1981, 79674 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - England, 1983, 79673 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, June 1981, 79672 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Letters: Aug - Dec 1981, 79671 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1982, 79670 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1983, 79669 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1984, 79668 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - West Point, 1984-1985, 79667 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985, 79666 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Rice Alumni Trip to Rev. VA, Nov 1985, 79665 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1986, 79664 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1987, 79663 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1988, 79662 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1989, 79661 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1990, 79660 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1991, 79659 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1992, 79658 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - West Point, 1992-1993, 79657 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1993, 79656 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - DAHAC (Department of the Army Historical Advisory Committee, 1993, 79655 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1994, 79654 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1995, 79653 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1996, 79652 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - FLL Memorial, Oct 17 1996 - Oct 23 1998, 79651 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1997, 79650 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1998, 79649 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Library Pruning, 1998, 79648 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Handbook, Correspondence, and Minutes (Ad Hoc Committee), 1996-1998, 79647 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Suggestions for Changes in Faculty Handbook (FHB), 1998-1999, 79646 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - NOD Committee (Night of Decadence student party), Feb 1999, 79645 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1999, 79644 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Rev. War NPS Advisory Board, 2000-2001, 79643 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2000, 79642 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - US Legal, 2000-2001, 79641 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2001, 79640 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2002, 79639 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2002, 79638 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Honor Council Appeal Board, 2003, 79637 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Master of Liberal Studies, 2003, 79636 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2003, 79635 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Wildenthal, 2003-2007, 79634 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Seed, 2004, 79633 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 2004, 79632 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Seed Contract, 2004, 79631 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Masters/RA Selection Committee, 2005, 79630 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 2005, 79629 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Masters/RA Selection Commitee, Residue 2005, 79628 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 2006, 79627 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - South Asia Search, 2006-2007, 79626 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - US Senior Search, 2007, 79625 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2007, 79624 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - AAUP, 2008, 79623 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 2008, 79622 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2017 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Series III: Courses, 1972-2004; 79584; 2 Linear Feet; (2 boxes)
  - History 293/393: The Art of War, 2003-2004, 79620 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - History 293/393: Section Preferences Spring 2004, 79619 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - History 293/393: Examinations, Syllabi, 1976-2004, 79618 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - History 293/393: Lectures Part 1, 2004, 79617 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - History 293/393: Lectures Part 2, 2004, 79616 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - History 293/393: Lectures Part 3, 2004, 79615 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - History 294/394: War in the Modern World, 2003, 79614 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - History 294/394: Section Preferences, 2003, 79613 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - History 294/394: Syllabi, Exams, 1983-2001, 79612 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - History 294/394: Lectures Part 1, 1983-2001, 79611 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - History 294/394: Lectures Part 2, 1983-2001, 79610 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - History 294/394: Lectures Part 3, 1983-2001, 79609 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - History 403 404, 2003-2004, 79608 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - History 466b: Spring 1972 (Papers), 79607 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - History 466: Syllabi, 1985-2002, 79606 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - History 466: American Revolution, 2002-2003, 79605 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - History 515, 79604 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - History 515/516: Readings in Military History, 1995 2004, 79603 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - History 546: Graduate Reading Seminar in Military History, 2004, 79602 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - History 566: War and Revolution, 2003, 79601 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Course Evaluations, 1993-1994, 79600 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Submissions for Distribution Credit; 1 of 6, 1999, 79599 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Submissions for Distribution Credit; 2 of 6, 1999, 79598 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Submissions for Distribution Credit; 3 of 6, 1999, 79597 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Submissions for Distribution Credit; 4 of 6, 1999, 79596 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Submissions for Distribution Credit; 5 of 6, 1999, 79595 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Submissions for Distribution Credit; 6 of 6, 1999, 79594 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Proposals for Distribution Credit; 1 of 2, 2000, 79593 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Proposals for Distribution Credit; 2 of 2, 2000, 79592 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Distribution Course Requests; 1 of 3, 2001, 79591 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Distribution Course Requests; 2 of 3, 2001, 79590 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Distribution Course Requests; 3 of 3, 2001, 79589 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Distribution Course Committee Correspondence; 1 of 4, 1999-2001, 79588 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Distribution Course Committee Correspondence; 2 of 4, 1999-2001, 79587 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Distribution Course Committee Correspondence; 3 of 4, 1999-2001, 79586 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Distribution Course Committee Correspondence; 4 of 4, 1999-2001, 79585 (Box 13, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Biographical and Personal, 1969-1990; 79567; 1 Linear Feet; (1 box)
  - Vitae, 1967-1990, 79583 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Golf Club, 2001-2002, 2006-2007, 79582 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Journal of Military History, 1996-2009, 79581 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - College System, 1956, 1986-1997, 79580 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - HISD - Rice Seminar: American History; Fall 2002, 2003, 79579 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - History Department Meetings and Minutes, 2005 Policies, 79578 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Handbook; 1 of 4, 1996-1997, 79577 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Handbook; 2 of 4, 1996-1997, 79576 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Handbook; 3 of 4, 1996-1997, 79575 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Handbook; 4 of 4, 1996-1997, 79574 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Appointment Books; 1 of 5, 1969-1978, 79573 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Appointment Books; 2 of 5, 1979-1985, 79572 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Appointment Books; 3 of 5, 1986-1993, 79571 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Appointment Books; 4 of 5, 1994-2001, 79570 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Appointment Books; 5 of 5, 2002-2008, 79569 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1982-2004, 79568 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Vitae, 2010, 144054 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Appointment book, 2009, 144055 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Jameson Fellowship, 1997-2004, 144058 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Series V: Correspondence, 2008-2009, 144053
  - Correspondence, 2008-2009, 144056 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Series VI: Book - "Books and the British Army in the age of the American Revolution," 1998-2010, 144057
  - Correspondence, University of North Carolina Press, 2006-2010, 144059 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, general, 1998-2006, 144060 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Introduction: ideas for composition, from research notes, 144061 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Title, map, preface, contents and illustrations, 144062 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Revisions to Books on War, 144063 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Introduction:residue from composition, 144064 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Introduction: endnotes, 144065 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Scaffolding for essays on officers and their books, Part I, 144066 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Residue from composition, officers and their libraries, Part I, 144067 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Scaffolding for Books Preferred, bibliography, Part II, 144068 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Books Preferred: Sale Catalogues, Part II, 144069 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Residue composition: Books Preferred, Part II, 144070 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Scaffolding: Books not Taken, Part III, 144073 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Appendices A-E, 144072 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Proofreading notes, 144074 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Index, 144075 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - First complete text, 2006, 144077 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Revised typescript, 2008, 144078 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Copy edited typescript with corrections, Feb. 2010, 144079 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Page proofs with corrections, July 2010, 144080 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Book - Warfare in the Western World, 144081
  - Revision notes and correspondence, 2005-2009, 144082 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Series VIII: Correspondence and appointment books, 2010-2011, 158267
  - Appointment books, 2010-2011, 158268 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2010, 158269 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2011, 158270 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Series IX: Service and honors at Rice University, 158271
  - Newsclippings regarding service to Rice Estate and Gift planning 2010, Faculty Planning Handbook committee 1996-1998, and Dr. Gruber's high school alma mater, the Hill School (2010), 158272 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Gruber's George R. Brown Award for Excellence in Teaching, 2001, 158273 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Gruber's George R. Brown Award for Superior Teaching, 2003, 158274 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Scroll honoring Dr. Gruber as the Harris Masterson Jr. Chair in History, 158284 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Series X: Biographical and Personal, continued, 158285
  - The Hill School (high school alma mater) diploma, June 3, 1951, 158305 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - United States Army Command and General Staff College certificate for service as John F. Morrison Visiting Professor of Military History, July 1979-June 1980, 158306 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Photograph of Gruber on staff of Destroyer Squadron Five, USS Rowan (left to right: Ensign Ira Gruber, Lieutenant (unnamed), Lietenant Waldo, Captain H. P. Weatherwax. Circa 1957., 158307 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Council and Staff of the Institute of Early American History & Culture, Williamsburg, Virginia, Spring 1963, including Ira Gruber, 158327 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Family photos at Hanszen House including Gruber children, Talarah, Anna and Conrad, ca. 1968-1969, 158321 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Gruber family at Hanzsen House being formally summoned to an event, ca. 1973, 158322 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Original score composed for Patricia and Ira Gruber's wedding, Sept. 13, 1958, by Robert Browne, who subsequently changed his name to Blaine Butler, 158334 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Portrait of Ira Gruber by Walton, April 1976, during Bicentennial of American Revolution, 158335 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Patricia and Ira Gruber at Duke University Commencement, June 1961, 158336 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Ira Gruber competing in U.S. Amateur Golf Championship in Seattle, WA, circa SUmmer 1952, while a sophomore at Duke University (photograph), 158337 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Newsclippings regarding Gruber's golf competition, 1952, 158338 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Army Commander's Award for Public Service, awarded to Ira Gruber, 1980 (including photographs), 1993, 1996, 158339 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Appointment of Ira Gruber as a Reserve Officer in the U.S. Navy as an Ensign, 1955, 158340 (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Series XI: Addendum, 174639
  Scope and Contents